one of the consequences of Mo's law and
the performance improvements that we
expect to follow is the so-called memory
wall here's why we have it the processor
speed in terms of instructions per
second we have already said it can be
expected to roughly double every let's
say 2 years memory capacity which is how
many gigabytes of memory can we have in
the same size
module is also doubling every two years
but memory latency that is how long does
it take to do a memory operation has
only been
improving about 1.1 times every two
years so over time as years go by if we
plot the speed of processors and memory
we get something like this an
exponential curve for the processors and
we get another exponential curve but
that grows a lot slower for memories
this here is the gap between processor
performance and me memory performance at
some time and then several years later
we have a much wider Gap this problem is
often called the memory wall basically
our processors are getting a lot faster
than memories are yet they have to
access memory every so many instructions
and because this difference in speed has
been growing very quickly over many
years we have been using caches as a
sort of stairs for the memory wall so
processors now are accessing caches
which are fast and only those rare
accesses that Miss in the cache will end
up going to the slow main memory we will
spend several lessons talking about how
to do caches and so on but this is just
one of the trends that we have to worry
about when we design processors is that
they do get faster but if the memory
doesn't get faster as quickly as they do
we have to continuously keep improving
our caches just to allow the processors
to not suffer from the much much slower
memory